<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Swearing denyed in the New Covenant and its pretended foundation rased. VVith the remnant of lies swept away. And the great and glorious name of Jesus highly exalted, above every name, to which powerful name, all swearers, and false swearers, and lyars, fighters, plotters, and persecutors, who are in the strife against the Son of God, must bow and submit, or be broken in pieces, for his wrath is kindled and his glittering sword is whet, to take vengeance of all those that will not have him to reign over them, in truth and righteousnesse, to the glory of God the Father. By Morgan Watkins.</title>
            <author>Watkins, Morgan, fl. 1653-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225425</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897938</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897938</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2558:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Swearing denyed in the New Covenant and its pretended foundation rased. VVith the remnant of lies swept away. And the great and glorious name of Jesus highly exalted, above every name, to which powerful name, all swearers, and false swearers, and lyars, fighters, plotters, and persecutors, who are in the strife against the Son of God, must bow and submit, or be broken in pieces, for his wrath is kindled and his glittering sword is whet, to take vengeance of all those that will not have him to reign over them, in truth and righteousnesse, to the glory of God the Father. By Morgan Watkins.</title>
                  <author>Watkins, Morgan, fl. 1653-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Wilson at the sign of the Black-Spread-Eagle and Windmill in Martins Le-Grand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swearing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135735:1"/>
            <p>SWEARING DENYED IN THE New Covenant, And its pretended foundation RASED.</p>
            <p>VVith the remnant of lies ſwept away. And the great and glorious name of Jeſus highly exalted, above every name, to which powerful Name, all Swearers, and falſe Swearers, and Lyars, Fighters, Plotters, and Perſecutors, who are in the ſtrife againſt the Son of God, muſt bow and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, or be broken in pieces, for his wrath is kindled and his glittering ſword is whet, to take venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of all thoſe that will not have him to reign over them, in Truth and Righteouſneſſe, to the glory of God the Father.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Morgan Watkins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmill</hi> in <hi>Martins Le-Grand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135735:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135735:2"/>
            <head>Swearing denyed in the New Covenant, and its preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Foundation raſed; with the Remnant of lyes ſwept away.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg>Eſus Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever; him hath God the Father high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exalted, and given him a name, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove every Name, that at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that every tongue ſhould confeſſe, that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the glory of God the Father, <hi>Phil.</hi> 29.10.11. Now if he be Lord, wherein is he honoured? is it not in obeying his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and doing the thing that he ſaith? as he ſaith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſobedient; <hi>Why call you me Lord Lord, and do not the things which I ſay?</hi> ſo it appeareth he that obeyes him not, hath nothing to do to call him Lord, for he whom he obeyes is his Lord; as its written, his Servants ye are whom ye obey; he only enters the Kingdome that doth the will of the Father, and this is the will of the Father, that we ſhould hear his Son; <hi>For this is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed, heare ye him,</hi> of him <hi>Moſes</hi> Propheſied ſaying, <hi>him ſhall ye heare in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you, and every ſoul that will not hear that Prophet, ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people, Act.</hi> 3.22, 23. And this is the day of tryal in this Nation, who will heare him, or refuſe him; Who will chuſe to obey him, or man; who will fear him, or fear man: And ſaith <hi>Solomon, the fear of man bringeth a ſnare,</hi> Pro. 29.25. which thing is now witneſſed, whereby Thouſands are catched, and under Condemnations; <hi>but who ſo putteth his truſt in the Lord ſhall be ſafe,</hi> which thing alſo is known to the obedient, and ſhall alſo be known to the ſorrow of the diſobedient, for he will ſuddenly appear for us and plead our cauſe, and make the innocency of it appear to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about, that they may fear and tremble before him; who will make his Name glorious, which the Father
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135735:3"/>hath given him, and is, and ſhall be known to be <hi>above very Name,</hi> which Name is a ſtrong Tower, and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not in this Name, is condemned already; and this is the condemnation, that Light is come into the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Into which thoſe that are gathered, and fly unto, are ſafe, for his preſence and Power is felt in the middeſt of them, <hi>and his glorious voice is heard in Sion;</hi> where he raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, let the people tremble at his great and terrible Name, for it is holy and great in <hi>Sion,</hi> and he is high above all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Therefore exalt the Lord our God and worſhip at his holy Hill, for the Earth ſhall know we are his people, and the Sheep of his Paſture, and his truth (into which we are gathered) ſhall be exalted to all Generations; <hi>but the way of the wicked ſhall be turned upſide down,</hi> and that vain wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that teaches for Doctrines the Commandments of men, <hi>Mat</hi> 15.9. Theſe be the blind guides that lead the blind people into the ditch; but Chriſt teacheth his Diſciples to beware of their leaven, that was their Doctrine, which then would have made voyd the commands of God, and now would make voyd, or of no effect the Commands of his Son whom the Father hath given for a Commander to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>and he that obeyes him not, ſhall be cut off from his people;</hi> but his Sheep heare his voyce, and keep his ſayings, <hi>who ſaith, ſwear not at all;</hi> And herein is he acknowledged to be Lord, by the doing of the thing he ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.46. and this is to the glory of God the Father, who hath highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted him, and given him a Name above every Name, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Abraham,</hi> above <hi>Moſes,</hi> above <hi>David,</hi> above the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and above the Angels, above every tongue of men &amp; Angels, that have ſworn, who muſt bow to his Commands <hi>(who ſaith ſwear not at all)</hi> and confeſs that he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, to the glory of God the Father, who ſaith every knee ſhall bow, <hi>and let all the Angels of God worſhip him, whoſe throne is for ever and ever;</hi> A Scepter of righteouſneſs is the Scepter of thy Kingdome, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6.8. who ſaid, <hi>Lo I come to do thy will O God,</hi> he taketh away the firſt, that he may eſtabliſh the ſecond, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.9.</p>
            <p>Now that which was an ordinance in old time, he taketh away, ſaying it hath been ſaid by them of old time, thou
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135735:3"/>ſhalt not for-ſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thy Oaths; this of old was a ſervice of God under the firſt Covenant which was of works) to ſwear and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their oaths; this was a work acceptable to God, <hi>But the ſecond Covenant being eſtabliſhed upon better premiſes,</hi> wherin God freely gave his own Son to be his Salvation to the ends of the Earth; to bring that forth in man, which he requireth of him; <hi>By writing his Law in his heart, and putting his words in his inward parts,</hi> whereby he comes to know the Lord, and be taught of him to know himſelf to be nothing, but what he is in, and through him, who hath all power; So of our ſelves we can do nothing, therefore we cannot properly ſwear, being not our own, (<hi>Mark</hi>) nor of abillity to perform of our ſelves, any good thing, much leſs an Oath to the Lord, for we who are come into the true reſt, <hi>are not to think our own thoughts, nor ſpeak our own words,</hi> for Chriſt commanded to take no thought for our life, what to eat or drink or put on, <hi>becauſe we have not power of ourſelves,</hi> to add to ourſelves; for which of you by taking thought can add one Cubit to his Stature, therefore take no thought, or promiſe to your ſelves, nor ſwear to do this, or that, or the other, for the power is in another, by whom you draw your breath; Therefore we cannot promiſe any thing ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, being not our own, <hi>nor born of the will of man, (then how can we ſwear)</hi> that ſtand not in our own wills, but in the will of him who ſaith <hi>ſwear not at all;</hi> for the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> reproveth abſolute promiſing, without relation to him who hath the power, <hi>go to now ye that ſay, To day and to morrow we will do ſuch a thing, James,</hi> 4.13. <hi>Whereas ye know not whether ye ſhall live till to morrow, for that ye ought to ſay if the Lord will,</hi> verſe the 15. Now to ſay, I will ſwear if the Lord will, or if the Lord help me, is a tempting of God, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of him to help to break his own command, or to help him to perform that, which he commands him not to do; therefore leave off now ye ſwearers, and falſe ſwearers, and forcers to ſwear, for the Lord will rebuke you with his fiery indignation.</p>
            <p>For the power that ſhould perform the Oath is in him who is the Oath, Truth and Covenant of God to us, &amp; ends the <hi>Jews</hi> Oaths and Covenant, <hi>who ſaith ſwear not at all,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:135735:8"/>(why) becauſe ſaith Chriſt, (that hath all power) <hi>thou canſt not make one hair white or black,</hi> ſo here is man's power and abſoluteneſs denyed; who could not keep the firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which became to him unprofitable, <hi>in that it was weak, Heb.</hi> 7.18. So he who required perfect obedience, <hi>finding fault with it, which could make nothing perfect, took it away,</hi> that he might eſtabliſh the ſecond in which alone God's power Chriſt Jeſus is abſolute: who hath obtained it, by the denyal of his own will as he was man, and in that his State of humiliation, took not upon him abſoluteneſs, but ſaid <hi>I can do nothing of my ſelf, Joh.</hi> 5.30. and here ſware not, or as I may ſay from his own words, could not ſwear of himſelf, for himſelf he denyed, but <hi>confeſſed,</hi> (which word <hi>Confeſſe</hi> under the Law was <hi>Swear</hi>) to the glory of the God the Father, in whom the power was abſolute, and therefore he might ſwear, who was of all power to perform his Oaths, <hi>Who is the head of Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. <hi>who ſware not, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all whoſe head he is, not to ſwear at all, ſo he that ſwears diſhonoureth his head,</hi> and doth contrary to his Command, and alſo his example, who whileſt he walked upon Earth, it cannot be proved he ſware at all, and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>he that ſaith he abideth in him, ought himſelf alſo ſo to walk even as he walked,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.6. Now he that ſwears breaks his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, diſhonours him whom he calls Lord, and walks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to him, who is given to his people for an example and leader, a Commander, and the Captain of their Salvation, the oath of God, who ends oaths, and did not ſwear, <hi>but made a good Confeſſion,</hi> to the glory of the Father, and ſaid <hi>ſwear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if any ſay, though we have not power, and are not abſolute of our ſelves, we ſwear but to our power, and ſo ſay, help me God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thou haſt not power thou art not to ſwear, leaſt thou forſwear thy ſelf; and if thy power be in Chriſt, thou canſt not expect that he will give it thee, to break his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>without me ye can do nothing, John</hi> 15.5. that is to ſay well-pleaſing to God; but it is not well-pleaſing to him to break his Commands, (as many can now witneſs that have done it to their miſery, who are under dreadful
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135735:8"/>Judgement tormented:) Now he that ſwears ſins, and doth it againſt Chriſt, and ſo without him, <hi>for in him is no ſin;</hi> but the power of darkneſſe being head, and the eye blind, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Command ſhould be ſeen and felt to be the will of God, the underſtanding comes to be darkned, and man takes counſel in this ſtate of his enemy, the <hi>Judas</hi> in his own heart, who betrayes him by a pretence of liberty, and thereby brings him in to bondage, and condemnation; but where the power is witneſſed the Command is kept, which denieth ſwearing, and cannot call God to help to break the Command of his Son, whom he hath ſent to do his will, in whom he is well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpake of ſwearing, and as we judge, hath relation to the Goſpel times, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus our great <hi>High-Prieſt, Prophet,</hi> and <hi>King</hi> is come, is whom the Law and the Prophets are fulfilled and ended, and he that is in him is in Truth, and as he walks in Truth he anſwers the witneſſe of God in all mens Conſciences, which is a ſurer Teſtimony then an Oath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>it ſtands in the power of God, and the endleſſe life;</hi> ſo that the life of the Son of God, manifeſted in man, and reaching to the witneſſe of God in all Conſciences, ends the occaſion of an Oath, cauſed through unbelief, or doubting of the Truth in a man; for one who is in Chriſt, to put his Brother who is in Chriſt to ſwear, becauſe he cannot believe him, is as it were to undervalue or put a lye upon the Truth, <hi>and diſhonour the holy Name by which he is called,</hi> for he that is in Chriſt, knoweth that he which is born of him cannot lye, <hi>for he is kept by the mighty power of God, that the wicked one toucheth him not, John</hi> 5.18. ſo among the Brethren in Chriſt there is no place for an Oath, for there is no ſtrife, there is no lye, there is no fighter, plotter, killer, murtherer, nor diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſon, <hi>but here is the true fear of God, and they that honour the King,</hi> here is Chriſt the head of his Church, and every Member is his own order: &amp; thoſe who trouble them, when they have all ſaid, &amp; done, ſcandalized, reproached, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted them, and tormented themſelves with their vain labour, muſt lye down in ſorrow and confeſſe, theſe are the Kings beſt Subjects, who lift not a hand againſt him, neither
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135735:4"/>can plot, nor contrive the leaſt evil againſt his Perſon and juſt power; for what they do againſt his Perſon, or juſt power, they do againſt their own life, and the Truth they do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe; for as we abide in the Truth, we can do no wrong to him nor any man elſe, for Truth cannot wrong any man, neither thoſe that are in it, but labours for the good of all men, <hi>that all might come to the knowledge of it and be ſaved,</hi> for he that walks in this path <hi>muſt do to every man, as he would have every man to do to him,</hi> and this Law ſhall out-live all Laws to the contrary, and this way, and they that walk in it, ſhall proſper, and all other ſhall ſoon decay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome may ſay, though ſome may be believed that walk as Chriſtians, yet others that walk in deceit are not to be believed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay, that thoſe who are not in Truth are not to be believed though they ſwear, for being in the tranſgreſſion are captivated by the power of darkneſſe, <hi>who rules in the Children of diſobedience,</hi> and theſe make little Conſcience of an Oath, and leſſe to break it; for it is grown a faſhion or cuſtom to take it, and alſo to break it, for you may ſee how little ſtead it ſtood the King in formerly, and how little it advantaged all the ſeveral powers ſince, and it will ſtand them in as little ſtead now, who truſt to it; for how did the Magiſtrates under the former powers, ſwear againſt King and Houſe of Lords, (and it may be had ſworn once or twice before) and now ſwear for that which formerly they ſwore againſt, there are but few but who are in the Truth that will looſe any thing for want of ſwearing, as is made manifeſt to all that can ſee; and alſo thoſe that love the Pope, and thoſe that love the works of the Devil, are unlikely by ſwearing to come to love the King, or be made true Subjects to him, <hi>but thoſe that love God, and keep his Commands,</hi> are they that truly <hi>honour the King,</hi> and will be found faithful to him.</p>
            <p>But ſomething further to the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> his words, which are, <hi>and be that ſweareth in the earth ſhall ſwear by the God of Truth,</hi> but he that is <hi>redeemed from the earth</hi> ſweareth not in the earth, but abiding in the Truth <hi>ſwears not at all, for the former things are paſt away,</hi> and the Son of God is come, the promiſe of God in whom the Prophets end, <hi>and all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135735:4"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God in him are yea, and in him Amen, unto the glory of God by us,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. for the word of God, the Son of God, Jeſus Chriſt the Truth of God, who was preached among the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuths</hi> by the Apoſtle and others, <hi>was not yea and nay, but in him was yea;</hi> and he that abides in the word, and the word in him, as in the Son of God, <hi>who is yea, and amen,</hi> in Truth and Righteouſneſſe is in yea, but againſt Truth and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is in nay, <hi>and what is more then this cometh of evil;</hi> but he that is in ſwearing is in the tranſgreſſion, out of the Truth, and fallen under Condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> prophecying in the time of the Law, when ſwearing was lawful, as Circumciſion, and other Ordinances were, <hi>as meats, and drinks, and divers waſhings, and carnal Ordinances impoſed on them until the time of Reformation, Heb.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. and the Prophet ſpeaking of the calling of the Gentiles, who knew not God, nor ſware by his Name, but by their Idols and falſe Gods, and alſo of a remnant of the <hi>Jews</hi> that he would bring forth, out of a great number who were departed from him, <hi>that were as a ſmoke in his noſe, whoſe Name ſhould be left for a curſe, whom the Lord ſhould ſlay and call his Servants</hi> (both Jews and Gentiles that ſought him) <hi>by another Name,</hi> who were to inherit his holy Mountain; the which glory he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by way of illuſtrating the Jews worſhip in its purity, which was to ſpeak to their capacity, figuring forth the glory to come, (which was to them inviſible) by their worſhip in its purity, which was viſible and outward, and alſo that they ſhould build houſes, and plant vineyards, and eat the fruit of them, and ſhould enjoy the work of their hands, and it ſhould be (ſpeaking by way of compariſon) <hi>as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael bring an Offering in a clean veſſel into the bonſe of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 66.20. <hi>And I will take of them for Prieſts, and for Levites, and it ſhall come to paſſe, that from one new Moon to another, and from one Sabbath to another, ſhall all fleſh come to worſhip before me ſaith the Lord,</hi> verſ. 21, 23. ſo here you may ſee the things mentioned under the Law, <hi>which are but the ſhadow of the good things under the Goſpel, and where the ſubſtance is come, the ſhadows are aboliſhed;</hi> and again, when it is ſaid under the Law, <hi>every tongue ſhall ſwear,</hi> when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> mentions the ſame Scripture in the time of the Goſpel <hi>(Mark) he ſaith every
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135735:5"/>tongue ſhall confeſſe to God,</hi> as for example, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 11. <hi>For it is written, as I live ſaith the Lord, every knee ſhall bow to me, and every tongue ſhall onfeſſe to God;</hi> Now ſee how it is written by the Prophet, where <hi>Paul</hi> quotes it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.23. where it is written, <hi>every knee ſhall bow, every tongue ſhall ſwear,</hi> here you may ſee plainly the Apoſtle changeth it from ſwear, <hi>to confeſs,</hi> becauſe ſwearing was not to among Chriſtians, and <hi>Paul</hi> again in the <hi>Philippians</hi> 2.10, 11. where it is again mentioned in theſe words, <hi>that every tongue ſhall confeſſe</hi> (and not ſwear) <hi>that Jeſus is the Lord,</hi> and here you may plainly ſee, that the Commandement being changed, there was as neceſſity that the words ſhould be changed, according to the command of him who ſaid <hi>ſwear not at all,</hi> that his Name may be known <hi>to be above every Name of men and Angels;</hi> Now this were enough for thoſe that are not blind, to ſee the Command changed by the Apoſtle himſelf, but thoſe that will not hear the voice of his Son, who ſpeaks in their Conſciences, will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hear the voice of his Servants, though they ſpeak by his Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now I come to lay before you the Command of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>James,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>But above all things my Brethren ſwear not, neither by Heaven, neither by the Earth,</hi> (Mark) <hi>neither by any other Oath, but let your yea be yea, and your nay nay, leaſt ye fall into Condemnation,</hi> James 5.12.</p>
            <p>Conſider, above all things, is a word of mighty impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that above all ſnares of the Devil, we keep out of this, which above all things brings ſuch diſhonour to our Lord Chriſt; (but thoſe that know not his glorious Name, are blind in this thing) for above all things in this his glory is chiefly concerned, <hi>who is Gods Oath, and Covenant in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and truth,</hi> and every true Chriſtian is in Chriſt, <hi>Gods Covenant, in righteouſneſſe and truth,</hi> firſt being in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (is not in himſelf) but in the power of God. 2. Being in his Righteouſneſſe, can do no wicked thing, and therefore an Oath is uſeleſſe here, for it undervalues the power and righteouſneſſe of God, <hi>his Oath and Covenant,</hi> which is to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate us again in his own image, in his Son Chriſt Jeſus, which is the birth that ſins not, which the wicked one cannot touch, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.18.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135735:5"/>
            <p>Thirdly, he that is in the Truth Chriſt, is in that which the Devil is out of, <hi>and there is no lye in Chriſt the Truth,</hi> and the that is in him ſpeaks the Truth, and doth the Truth that he is in, the Spirit of Truth that cannot lye; but he that ſwears he will be true, anſwers not the witneſſe of God in mens Conſciences, but rather judges himſelf not true, but will be, and this will which is out of the truth is mans, in which the power is not, <hi>for 'tis not in him that willeth, Rom.</hi> 9.16. for Chriſt the Truth is the will of the Father, brought forth in every true Chriſtian, <hi>which will is our ſanctification,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.3. <hi>The word is truth which ſanctifies, ſanctifie them through thy word, thy Word is Truth, John</hi> 17.17. and he that is ſanctified through the Truth, ſheweth forth the Life, Truth, and Righteouſneſſe of God, which ends Promiſes and Oaths, in him who is Yea and Amen for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>But the true honour, in which God the Father is glorified, is in confeſſing that his Son Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, in bowing and ſubmitting to his great Name, (which is his power) in giving obedience to his Commands, though it coſt us the loſſe of all, even the laying down of our outward lives; <hi>this is a good confeſſion,</hi> and as Chriſt himſelf who ſware not, <hi>but made a good confeſſion before Pontius Pilate,</hi> in the obedience of his Fathers Commands, and ſubmitted to the death, and abode in his Love, and obtained a Name, <hi>which is above every name,</hi> and as he abode in his Fathers love, ſo we muſt abide in his love, which is by giving up to the obedience of his Commands, who ſaith <hi>ſwear not at all,</hi> and thoſe who love him, and follow him, obey and honour him.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> who ſpake by his ſpirit, ſaid, <hi>above all things my Brethren ſwear not,</hi> and ſaith Chriſt <hi>if ye love me keep my Commandements, Joh.</hi> 14, 1. and ſaith <hi>Paul, if any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be acurſed,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. But they who impriſon and perſecute the people of God, becauſe they will not break the Commands of Chriſt, <hi>they love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and wo is their portion, it had been better they had never been born; for as many as are come into Chriſt, <hi>their yea is yea, and their nay nay,</hi> and are out of Condemnation; <hi>for there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt,</hi> but where their yea is not yea, nor their nay nay,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135735:6"/>they are out of the truth, and there is the lying, ſwearing, and for-ſwearing, and ſwearing cannot bring into the truth, for it is againſt Chriſt the Truth, and <hi>James</hi> his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Apoſtle of truth, and is under the Condemnation.</p>
            <p>But the Common Objection among men (who know not the truth) is this, which <hi>Paul</hi> mentions in the 6. of the <hi>Heb.</hi> and the 16. In theſe words; <hi>for men verily ſwear by the greater, and an Oath for Confirmation is to them</hi> (mark not to us) <hi>an end of all ſtrife</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtle in this place mentioning the practices of men, which ſware in the old time, who ſware by the greater, that it might be the greater ingagement to them to perform their Oaths, and to <hi>confeſs</hi> the God of Heaven to be the greater, becauſe it was the practice among men to ſwear by the greater, and a command to the Jews ;<hi>and ſo the Lord willing more abundantly to confirm his promiſes to the ſeed, ſware to man by himſelf,</hi> who was the greateſt, (that in old time) men were to ſwear by; but in the new Covenant <hi>old things were done away, and all things were become new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if it be ſaid the Apoſtle ſpake to the preſent practice among men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay it may be the practice among the Jews at this day, who are <hi>in the unbelief cut off;</hi> but if it be, it is ſin to them, as is all the reſt of their Ordinances <hi>which are ended in Chriſt,</hi> being that thereby they go about, (by the practice of them) to eſtabliſh a righteouſneſs of their own, <hi>endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make voyd the righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> who by their practice deny him to be come, to whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>If ye believe not that I am he, you ſhall dye in your ſin, and whither I go ye cannot come, Job.</hi> 8.21.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> And again if it be ſaid, that it was then a practice among men, <hi>and an Oath or Confimation is to them an end of all ſtrife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay it is a practice among men at this day, who are in ſtrife, but both theſe practices, ſwearing, and ſtrife, are evil, and under Condemnation, being both out of the truth, againſt Chriſts Command &amp; practice, and againſt the Apoſtles Command, and the practice of them who walked in truth, and it is ſo common now, that it is grown into a form
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135735:6"/>of ungodlineſſe, and all in it are far from truth, that they cannot believe one another, without an oath, nor then neither; for as ſwearing is common, ſo alſo is for-ſwearing, for without an oath little Law or Juſtice is to be had, nor then neither, for him who is in truth; but if a man can ſwear, he may ſoon have a Lawyer to lye for him, if he be well paid before-hand, for he can draw up a form of lyes, and ſay it is a form of Law; And this is the way men take to end their money, and to begin the ſtrife, which many times continues while their money laſts, and then it may ſoon be ended at home, by their neighbours, for theſe things the Land mourns, and grones under theſe heavy burthens.</p>
            <p>Again, if it were a practice among men, let us conſider what men it were, that it was practiced among, whether they are men of the World, or men in Chriſt, (which were new men) but I ſhall make it appear, to be among the men of the World, the carnal men who were in ſtrife, and there the oath, and ſwearing was to end it; but Chriſt the Truth, where he is received, and witneſſed, ſtrife comes to be ended, &amp; the Oath not to be uſed; but that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear what men it were, read <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.14, 15, 16. <hi>But if ye have bitter envying and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not, and lye not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth; this wiſdome is earthly, ſenſual and diveliſh, for where envying and ſtrife is</hi> (mark) <hi>there is Confuſion and every evil work.</hi> Can any be ſo blind as to think theſe things were among the Apoſtles, and owned and practiced among the Brethren of Chriſt, who walked in the Spirit? for theſe were the fruits of the fleſh, the works of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which is Confuſion, <hi>and there is every evil work,</hi> which was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the elect People of God; for thoſe that are carnal, <hi>walk as men</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> what men? Such that are in ſtrife, and ſwearing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 3. <hi>For ye are yet carnal, for whereas there is among you, envying and ſtrife, and Diviſions, are ye not carnal and walk as men?</hi> Here is the word <hi>men,</hi> anſwering the words, for <hi>men</hi> verily ſwear, which <hi>men</hi> you ſee the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles reproves here and in divers places, and in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12.13. <hi>Let us therefore caſt off the works of darkneſs, and let us put on the Armor of Light, let us walk honeſtly as in the day, not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135735:7"/>in Rioting and drunkenueſs, nor in Chambering and wantonneſs,</hi> (mark) <hi>not in ſtrife and envying, but put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> Here you may ſee that ſtrife is condemned to be one of the works of darkneſs, in ſuch who had not put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and theſe be the <hi>men</hi> that have not put on Chriſt, who are in <hi>ſtrife</hi> and ſwear to end it, and ſaith <hi>Paul, let nothing be done through ſtrife,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Phil</hi> 2, 3. <hi>And the Servant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, Tim.</hi> 2.2. So it is ſufficently proved, that the Oath and Swearing was among them that walked not in Chriſt the Truth, but among ſuch that were Carnal, and walked in darkneſs, in which they are now that are in envying and <hi>Strife,</hi> which be evil works; and they that ſwear do another evil work to end it, and here the beginning and the end is evil, being the work of the Devil.</p>
            <p>But the Children of the Light, (whom the dark World in ſcorn call Quakers) <hi>are come to the word which was in the beginning,</hi> (who ends the firſt Covenant) <hi>even to Jeſus the Mediator of the New Covenant, and to the blood of ſprinkling, that ſpeaketh better things then the blood of Abel;</hi> and we cannot refuſe, nor turn away from his voyce, <hi>who now ſpeaks from Heaven</hi> (which ſhakes both Heaven and Earth) for we who are faithfull, and hear the beloved Son of God, (who ſaith <hi>ſwear not at all, we do receive a Kingdome which cannot be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> (which is not of this World, therefore the World ſeeth it not) and having grace whereby we may ſerve him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably, cannot but <hi>obey, reverence, and fear our God, who as a conſuming ſire;</hi> And now for the obedience of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, whom we <hi>ſerve, reverence and fear,</hi> are we perſecuted and impriſoned, (by thoſe who neither ſerve nor fear him) and our goods ſpoyled, contrary to the Law of God, and alſo of the Nation; but in all theſe things we rejoyce, and are more then Conquerers, thorow him that hath loved us, whoſe power and glorious preſence is witneſſed among us; and his love is felt, in filling of us with the joy of his ſpirit, by which we can freely forgive all our enemies, and pray that thoſe who diſpitefully uſe us, may come to ſee their wicked way, to the way of righteouſneſſe, where they may find mercy and be ſaved; But if they will not hear, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, nor ſpeedily leave off the evil of their doings; I ſay <hi>Our God who is a conſuming fire,</hi> the Lord who is riſen to plead
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135735:7"/>the Innocency of our cauſe, which is come before him, who is the God of the whole Earth, to whom all vengance belongs, he will recompence them according to their deeds.</p>
            <p>And is it not a ſhame for men, who would be called Chriſtians, to perſecute, and impriſon thoſe who obey Chriſt, and keep his Commands, for obeying him, and keeping his Commands, and walking as they have him, and his Apoſtles, for an example? who ſaid <hi>let us hold faſt the Profeſſion of our faith without wavering, not forſakeing the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſum is, but exhort one a nother, following peace with all men, and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> and who is he that can accuſe us, that we have not followed <hi>peace</hi> in our meetings, and <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in our converſations? but they it be who neither love peace, nor holineſs in their Converſations, that diſturb us in our peaceable meetings, and Aſſemblies, as the manner of the Churches of Chriſt were, and now are, <hi>who worſhip the Lord in ſpirit and in truth,</hi> and as we are kept and abide in the truth, we can injure no man; but walking in love, <hi>and doing to all men, as we would have all men ſhould do to us; But all men</hi> (though they may be called Chriſtians) <hi>have not faith,</hi> and theſe are the unreaſonable men, who make warr againſt the Lamb and his followers; becauſe they do ſhew forth that life, which they that perſecute them do profeſſe, and therein they are unreaſonable and cruel; <hi>For if every one who names the Name of Jeſus, did depart from iniquity,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution would ſoon ceaſe, &amp; Love would increaſe; <hi>but wo to the wicked, it ſhall be ill with him;</hi> but his bleſſing is, &amp; ſhall be <hi>with his ſeed,</hi> and his ſpiritual preſence with his <hi>off-ſpring,</hi> which hath bloſſomed, and budded, and ſhall fill the face of the Earth with fruit.</p>
            <p>From one who waits to ſee the Lord exalt himſelf, over all this Enemies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Morgan Watkins.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Albans Common Goale,</hi> 
                  <date> this 7th. <hi>of the</hi> 12th <hi>Month,</hi> 1660</date>
               </dateline>
               <hi>Where I now ſuffer bonds for the truth of God, and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
